1/7



CONTACT

1524 Prestwick Drive Orleans, ON K1E 1S5 Canada

+1 (613) 413-5918 joachim@agou.ca joachimagou@asme.org http://joa.im

LANGUAGES

English (Bilingual)
French (Native).
Spanish (Limited working)
Italian (Elementary)
Hebrew (Elementary)

CERTIFICATIONS

Working at Heights Training Aerial Lifts & Aerial Work Platforms

Fall Protection - Safety Training Elevated Work Platform -SafetyTraining Airport Security Awareness Training Certificate

Emergency First Aid – CPR and

AED

PUBLICATIONS

Emission Measurements of VariousBiofuels using a Commercial Swirl-Type Air-Assist Dual Fuel Injector

Comparative Study for Biodiesel Properties and Standards for Gas Turbine

JOACHIM AGOU

Mechanical Aerospace Engineer | Systems Integration Project Engineering | Project Management

Experienced mechanical aerospace engineer with a combined 10+ years of dedication and proven ability in project engineering, prototype design/development, systems integration, quality assurance, and manufacturing methodologies.

Throughout my various positions and projects in Aerospace and Energy industry, I always had pleasure forming trust-based relationships, solving complex customer problems, and leading teams to achieve challenging goals.

My guiding principles are simple: work hard, lead by example and deliver a positive impact on every professional and personal engagement.

EXPERIENCE

MDS Aero Support Corporation Gas Turbine Applications Engineer (Systems Integrator)

December 2013 — Present

Ottawa (ON), Canada

- Develop and deploy engine test facilities and test systems for aviation and industrial Gas
 Turbines with emphasis on Instrumentation and Software integration.
 - A few projects I worked on:

Maintenance, Repair, and Overhaul (MRO) facilities:

- ✓ Air France Industries KLM Engineering & Maintenance (France) CFM56, GE90, GP7200, GEnx
- ✓ GKN Aerospace (Sweden) Volvo RM12 (Gripen fighter jet)
- ✓ Vector Aerospace (Canada) P&WC JT15D (multiple variants)
- ✓ Lockheed Martin Commercial Engine Solutions (Canada) CFM56 (multiple variants)
- ✓ Safran Aircraft Engine Services Morocco (Morocco) CFM56 (multiple variants)

Research and Development (R&D) facilities:

- ✓ Rolls-Royce/ NASA Stennis Space Center (USA) Outdoor Jet Engine Test Facility (development and certification testing)
- ✓ Safran Aircraft Engines (formerly Snecma) (France) CFM LEAP (certification testing), CFM56 (endurance testing)
- ✓ MAN Energy Solutions (Germany) Industrial Gas Turbine MGT6000-2S, MG8000-1S
- ✓ MDS AeroTest/ GLACIER Test Facility (Canada) Emissions system support
- ✓ AVIC Commercial Aircraft Engines (ACAE) / Aeroengine Corporation of China (AECC) (China) – Fan, Booster, HPC, and Turbine (development testing)
- Define the relevant engine and facility parameters to be measured and calculated by the Data Acquisition System (DAS) for engine turbine testing.
- Configure Data Acquisition System (DAS), prepare post-analysis report templates, create realtime display pages, and automate test sequences to meet customer needs.
- Design the customer's operations consoles and the integration of HMI to control and monitor the DAS and facility equipment.
- Support customer's operations of engine testing during and beyond the commissioning phase (Field Service Representative) for extended periods (6+ months).
- Prepare and review technical documents: Engineering Specifications (ES), Design Briefs (DB), drawings (GA), Purchase Requests (PR), and Engineering Coordination Memos (ECM) for data

- acquisition software components, control/test systems, console design, and customer support.
- Write and run in-house and on-site Acceptance Test Procedures (ATP) to validate deliverables comply with contract technical and commercial requirements.
- Participate in on-site installation and commissioning of the Data Acquisition System (DAS), including performing on-site Acceptance Test Procedures (ATP) with clients.
- Use knowledge gained in the test cell environment to guide other engineering departments in the interpretation of customer requirements, and the design solutions required to meet those needs.
- Provide on-site and remote customer training in collaboration with Customer Service.

Siemens Canada (formerly Rolls-Royce Canada), Research and Technology Combustion & Pollutant Emissions Engineer - Aerothermal (intern)

January 2013 — August 2013

Montreal (QC), Canada

- Operated pollutants measurements with gas analyzers FTIR/FID/O₂ CEMS (Continuous Emission Monitoring Systems) - on Gas Turbine testbeds.
- Improved emissions data processing and analysis of non-conventional pollutants emissions.
- Evaluated the combustion performance of liquid (biodiesel blends) and gaseous (syngas blends) biofuels in terms of smoke & emissions and lean blow out.
- Characterized promising liquid and gaseous novel biofuels for use in industrial Gas Turbines to reduce greenhouse gases and potentially operation costs.
- Developed a robust numerical model for biofuels injection and combustion prediction (CFD).
- Compared biofuels with baseline fuels to examine the benefits while maintaining an acceptable overall combustion performance.

Combustion Research Laboratory at Laval University Research & Teaching Assistant with Dr. Alain De Champlain

January 2011 — December 2012

Quebec City (QC), Canada

- Developed biofuels (liquid & gaseous) applications for Gas Turbine and aircraft propulsion.
- Operated combustion gas emissions monitoring of swirl combustor via FTIR (Fourier Transformation Infrared) spectroscopy technology.
- Executed experimental tests of spray using PIV (Particle Image Velocimetry).
- Computed fluid dynamics prediction (CFD) of biodiesel spray including swirler configurations with emphasis on penetration depth, droplet size, velocity and spreading.
- Designed and assembled experimental apparatus, conducted experiments, trained, and supervised international summer interns.
- Hands on work like soldering electrical circuits, wiring instruments, and assembling process
 equipment (mass flow controllers, piping, pumps, pressure chambers, heaters, valves,
 injectors, and heat exchangers).
- Deployed Data Acquisition System (DAS), calibrated instrumentation, performed tests, and troubleshot problems.
- Compiled VBA program to collate and analyze a large volume of experimental data.
- Critically analyzed data after tests and correlated it with empirical evidence.
- Optimized the testing process to enhance data collection and established a benchmark for quantifying test results.
- Authored comprehensive technical reports to document test protocol, safety procedures, equipment laboratory, and findings.
- Successfully completed WHMIS and WORKSMART health and safety training programs.
- Prepared MAE Thermodynamics lectures, showed demonstrations of experiential exercises, supervised laboratory lectures, and evaluated laboratory reports.

updated February 2019 Joachim Agou / יהויקים אגו

online version available on LinkedIn 3/7

Florida Institute of Technology

Independent Study in Mechanical Engineering with Dr. Razvan Rusovici

January 2010 — June 2010

Melbourne (FL), USA

• Developed adaptive structures research and finite element analysis in fluid dynamics and acoustic via CAD and CAE software (Pro/E, ANSYS, and CFX).

Florida Tech Motorsports (FIT)

Formula SAE Series with Stephanie Hopper and Dr. Youngsik Choi

November 2008 — May 2009

Melbourne (FL) & Michigan International Speedway (MI), USA

- Supervised the powertrain division, dealing with engine management, differential, simulation, testing and optimization via CAD and CAE software (SolidWorks, Cosmos Design, and ANSYS).
- Designed and fabricated the composite bodywork.
- Created the Florida Tech Motorsports website.

Prestige Dentaire Service Engineer (intern)

June — July 2006 Nice, France

- Executed maintenance of dental equipment.
- Overhauled mechanical, plumbing, and electrical devices.

Tsahal, Israeli Army Training Program Military Experience (volunteer): Sar El Program

July — August 2005

Hatzerim Air Force Base, Israel

SKILLS & ABILITIES

- Industry Knowledge: System Integration, Systems Engineering, Project Engineering, Project Management, Aerospace Engineering, Business Strategy, Testing and Simulations
- Domain Expertise: Turbomachinery, Gas Turbines/ Jet Engines/Propulsion, Data Acquisition Systems, Aerodynamics, Thermodynamics, Combustion, Fluid Dynamics
- Tools & Technologies
 - Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD): ANSYS FLUENT, CFX, ANSYS ICEM CFD (Mesh Generation), GAMBIT.
 - Solid Modeling (CAD)/ Finite Element Analysis (FEA): AutoCAD, SolidWorks, Pro/ENGINEER & Creo, CATIA, ANSYS Workbench Platform, ANSYS Parametric Design Language (APDL), Cosmos Design, Solid Concepts, CNC Software/Mastercam.
 - Data Acquisition (DAQ): NI LabVIEW, proDAS (MDS Aero Support Corp), LaVision FlowMaster (PIV).
 - **Development Tools:** Matlab, Java, MS Excel/VBA, SQL, HTML Programming, LaTex, Mediawiki, Wi-Fi security and pentesting (Kali Linux).
 - Computer Skills: Microsoft Office, NetBeans, MATLAB, Mathcad, Maple, Adobe Dreamweaver, Adobe Photoshop/ Lightroom, Adobe Premiere Pro, VMWare (Virtualization), Linux.

updated February 2019 Joachim Agou / יהויקים אגו

- Interpersonal Skills: Problem Solving, Team Leadership, Engineering Management, Training, Teaching, Negotiation
- Languages: English (Bilingual), French (Native), Spanish (Limited working), Italian (Elementary), Hebrew (Elementary)

EDUCATION

Laval University

Master of Science (M.S.), Mechanical Engineering with Experimental Thesis. (ABD)

December 2013

Quebec City (QC), Canada

- Research Assistant (Combustion Laboratory).
- Teaching Assistant (MAE Thermodynamics).
- Laser Safety Certificate & WHMIS (Workplace Hazardous Materials Information System) qualified.
- Relevant courses completed:
 - Combustion Fundamentals (+CFD)
 - Internal Combustion Engines (+CFD)
 - Propulsion/ Air-breathing Engines (+CFD)
 - Data Acquisition and Signal Conditioning
 - o Systems Optimization
 - o Control Systems

Carleton University

Summer Program, Mechanical Engineering

Summer 2012

Ottawa (ON), Canada

 Experimental tests of spray using PIV (Particle Image Velocimetry) and PDPA (Phase Doppler Particle Analyzer).

Florida Institute of Technology

Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering (transfer student)*

May 2010

Melbourne (FL), USA

- Formula SAE member. Powertrain Division and Bodywork designer.
- Relevant courses completed:
 - o Computer-Aided Engineering
 - o Aerodynamics and Flight Mechanics
 - Design of Machine Elements
 - o Mechanical Vibrations
 - Fluid Mechanics (+Lab)
 - Heating Ventilation and Air Conditioning (HVAC)
 - Mechanical Engineering Design 2
 - o Thermal Systems Design
 - o Thermodynamics 2
 - Heat Transfer (+Lab)
 - o Control Systems
 - o Electric & Electronics Circuits
 - Theory of Machines
 - Materials Science and Engineering (+Lab)

online version available on LinkedIn 5/7

- o Calculus 3
- Boundary Value Problems
- o Technical Communication
- Engineering Economy & Planning
- Music Theory

SKEMA Business School (formerly Euro-American Institute of Technology) Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering (transfer student)*

January 2007

Sophia Antipolis, France

- Relevant courses completed:
 - Thermodynamics 1
 - Aerodynamics
 - Statics & Dynamics
 - o Deformable Solids
 - Physics 2 (+Lab)
 - o Computer Aided Design and Drafting
 - o Software Development: Java & C++
 - General Chemistry
 - o Ethics

Lycée Général et Technologique Les Eucalyptus

June 2004

Nice, France

High school, Baccalauréat Science Stream (S), Specialization Physics & Chemistry, Option Engineering Sciences.

PUBLICATIONS / CONFERENCE PAPERS

- J. Agou, B. Paquet & A. deChamplain. "Emission Measurements of Various Biofuels using a Commercial Swirl-Type Air-Assist Dual Fuel Injector" (with presentation), The Combustion Institute Canadian Section (CICS), Spring Technical Meeting, Université Laval, Quebec, Canada, May 13-16, 2013
- M. Youssef, J. Agou, B. Paquet & A. deChamplain. "Comparative Study for Biodiesel Properties and Standards for Gas Turbine" (with presentation), The Combustion Institute Canadian Section (CICS), Spring Technical Meeting, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada, May 13-16, 2012

CERTIFICATIONS & TRAININGS

- Aerial Lifts & Aerial Work Platforms, Worksite Safety Compliance Center, Certificate 156AWP-64
- Airport Security Awareness Training Certificate, Butterfly Aero Training, License GB81580A20140623
- Elevated Work Platform Safety Training, CRS Contractors Rental Supply
- Emergency First Aid Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) and automated external defibrillator (AED), Canadian Red Cross, Jennifer Sybrandy, Certificate 30200842
- AODA Customer Service Training, MDS Aero Support Corporation

^{*} Florida Institute of Technology and SKEMA Business School were part of a dual-degree program, and thus share a common graduation project.

- Fall Protection Safety Training, CRS Contractors Rental Supply
- Instant HR Workplace Hazards Training, MDS Aero Support Corporation
- Laser Safety Certificate, Université Laval, License CAN/CSA E-60825-1:03; IEC 60825-1
- Lockout/Tagout Control of Hazardous Energy Training, MDS Aero Support Corporation
- NEXUS, Canada Border Services Agency
- Occupational Health and Safety Awareness Training for Workers in Ontario, MDS Aero Support Corporation
- WHMIS Training, MDS Aero Support Corporation
- WHMIS (Workplace Hazardous Materials Information System), Université Laval
- Working at Heights Training, Safety Training Ottawa, Debbie Desaulniers

AWARDS

Engineering & Science Student Design Showcase

April 2009

Melbourne, FL

Best Mechanical Engineering Senior Design Project award with Formula SAE Project (Florida Tech Motorsports).

GROUPS & ASSOCIATIONS

- **❖** American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME), Member #102114839
- Society of Automotive Engineers International (SAE), Member since 2009
- ❖ Professional Engineers and Geoscientists Newfoundland & Labrador (PEGNL)

INTERESTS

Soccer, Karate (purple belt), Windsurfing (purple sail), Wakeboarding, Cycling, Skiing. Cinema, Music (DJ), Photography & Graphic Design, Traveling, High-Tech, Innovation.

REFERENCES

John Perrin

Manager of nxDAS group

MDS Aero Support Corporation, Suite 200, 1220 Old Innes Road, Ottawa, Ontario, K1B 3V3, Canada

Phone: +1 (613) 744-5794 x2358 E-mail: john.perrin@mdsaero.com

Qing Li

Software Specialist, Manager of Applications group

MDS Aero Support Corporation, Suite 200, 1220 Old Innes Road, Ottawa, Ontario, K1B 3V3, Canada

Phone: +1 (613) 744-5794 x2284 E-mail: <u>qing.li@mdsaero.com</u>

Christian Bourgeois

Director of Measurement Engineering

MDS Aero Support Corporation, Suite 200, 1220 Old Innes Road, Ottawa, Ontario, K1B 3V3, Canada

Phone: +1 (613) 744-5794 x2233

E-mail: christian.bourgeois@mdsaero.com

online version available on LinkedIn 7/7

Dr. Alain de Champlain

Director & Professor, Head of Combustion Research Laboratory.

Department of Mechanical & Aerospace Engineering

Laval University, 1065 Avenue de la Médecine, Quebec City, Quebec, G1V 0A6, Canada

Phone: +1 (438) 656-2131 x2198

E-mail: alain.dechamplain@gmc.ulaval.ca

Bernard Paquet

Research Engineer, Supervisor of Combustion Research Laboratory.

Department of Mechanical & Aerospace Engineering

Laval University, 1065 Avenue de la Médecine, Quebec City, Quebec, G1V 0A6, Canada

Phone: +1 (438) 656-2131 x6809 E-mail: <u>bernard.paquet@gmc.ulaval.ca</u>

Dr. Robert Gordon

Combustion Specialist, Team Leader of Research & Technology division.

Rolls-Royce Canada, 9500 Côte de Liesse, Montreal, Quebec, H8T 1A2, Canada

Phone: +1 (514) 636-0964 x7316

E-mail: robert.gordon2@rolls-royce.com

Dr. Yan Grasselli

Academic Head of Bachelor programs and Head of the Environmental and Marine Sciences Bachelor department.

SKEMA Business School, 60 rue Dostoïevski, 06902 Sophia Antipolis, France

Phone: +33 (0) 4 93 95 44 03 E-mail: yan.grasselli@skema.edu

Personal references available upon request.

updated February 2019 Joachim Agou / יהויקים אגו